# Nedjma Djouhra Ousidhoum

Email ndo24@cam.ac.uk

Citizenship Algerian

Birth 17-09-1990 Algiers, Algeria Webpage https://nedjmaou.github.io

Twitter @nedjmaou

Linkedin Nedjma Ousidhoum

#### Research Statement

I am a Postdoctoral Research Associate at the Department of Computer Science and Technology of the University of Cambridge. I work with Dr. Andreas Vlachos on fact-checking for journalists. Prior to this, I was a Ph.D. student at the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST) where I was working on multilingual toxic content detection and evaluation in NLP under the supervision of Dr. Yangqiu Song and Prof. Dit-Yan Yeung.

I am interested is NLP, computational social science, fairness and explainability.

### **Appointments**

**September 2021-now** Postdoctoral Research Associate at the University of Cambridge.

April 2021-September 2021 Postdoctoral Research Assistant at the University of Cambridge.

**September 2018-March 2021** Research Assistant at the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST).

**April 2014-September 2014** Postgraduate intern at the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST).

**December 2012-April 2014** Research Assistant at the University of Science and Technology Houari Boumedienne, Algiers, Algeria.

#### Education

Fall 2014-Summer 2021 PhD student at the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST).

**2010-2012** Master of Science in Software Engineering at the University of Science and Technology Houari Boumedienne, Algiers, Algeria.

**2007-2010** Bachelor of Science in Computer Science at the University of Science and Technology Houari Boumedienne, Algiers, Algeria.

## Teaching Experience

Spring 2018 Teaching Assistant of IT Entrepreneurship at HKUST.

Spring 2017 Teaching Assistant of Introduction to Natural Language Processing at HKUST.

**Spring 2016** Teaching Assistant of Multimedia Computing at HKUST.

Fall 2015 Teaching Assistant of the C Programming Bridging Course at HKUST.

 $<sup>^{1}\</sup>mathrm{I}$  am funded by the MONITIO project https://monitio-project.eu/

#### **Academic Services**

Diversity, Equity and Inclusion committee member (financial accessibility co-chair) at NAACL 2022.

Reviewer for EMNLP 2021, ACL 2021, NAACL 2021.

Secondary reviewer for COLING 2020, AAAI 2019.

Co-organizer of the North African in NLP<sup>2</sup> affinity group social at EMNLP 2020, COLING 2020, EACL 2021, NAACL 2021, ACL 2021.

#### **Publications**

**Nedjma Ousidhoum**, "On the Importance and Challenges of the Experimental Design of Multilingual Toxic Content Detection". *Ph.D. Thesis*. The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology.

**Nedjma Ousidhoum**, Xinran Zhao, Tianqing Fang, Yangqiu Song, Dit-Yan Yeung, "Probing Toxic Content in Large Pre-Trained Language Models" in Proceedings of the *ACL-IJCNLP* 2021.

**Nedjma Ousidhoum**, Yangqiu Song, Dit-Yan Yeung, "Comparative Evaluation of Label-Agnostic Selection Bias in Multilingual Hate Speech Datasets" in Proceedings of the *EMNLP* 2020.

**Nedjma Ousidhoum**, Zizheng Lin, Hongming Zhang, Yangqiu Song, Dit-Yan Yeung, "Multilingual and Multi-Aspect Hate Speech Analysis" in Proceedings of *EMNLP 2019*.

**Nedjma Ousidhoum**, Nacéra Bensaou, "Towards The Refinement of the Arabic Soundex" in Proceedings of *NLDB* 2013.

**Nedjma Ousidhoum**, Asma Bensalah, Nacéra Bensaou, "A New Classical Arabic Soundex Algorithm" in Proceedings of *The Second Conference on Advances in Communication and Information Technology (CIT 2012)*.

Asma Bensalah, **Nedjma Ousidhoum**, "Étude du Problème de la Correction Phonétique : État de l'art et Conception d'un Algorithme pour la Recherche Approchée dans un Dictionnaire de la Langue Arabe". *Master thesis*, Computer Science Department, University of Science and Technology Houari Boumedienne, Algiers, June 2012.

Venon Takaiteyi Mapfunde, **Nedjma Ousidhoum**, "Automatisation de la Procédure d'accessibilité dans les Réseaux de Petri Récursifs". *Bachelor thesis*, Computer Science Department, University of Science and Technology Houari Bomedienne, Algiers, June 2010.

#### **Talks**

**August 2021** Title *Challenges in Toxic Content Detection*. Language and Multimodal AI Lab (LAMA) Group Seminar (Imperial College London).

**November 2020** Title *The Experimental Design of Multilingual Hate Speech Detection*. Group Seminar of the Digital Technologies Research Center (National Research Council, Canada).

#### Grants and Awards

**2019-2020** The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology Scholarship.

August 2019 Student volunteer grant for IJCAI2019.

2018-2019 The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology Scholarship.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup>https://sites.google.com/view/NorthAfricansInNLP

2017-2018 The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology Scholarship.

2016-2017 The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology Scholarship.

**2015-2016** The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology Scholarship.

**2014-2015** The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology Scholarship.

**2012** Accepted at the Computer Science Ph.D. Program of the University of Science and Technology Houari Boumedienne, Algiers, Algeria.

#### Other

#### Languages

Arabic mother tongue.
French fluent (bilingual).
English fluent.

Programming Languages

Python, C, C++, Java.

#### Core Courses

Advanced Algorithms.
Theory of Computation.
Human Computer Interaction.
Computer Networks.
Knowledge Discovery in Databases.
Machine Learning.
Databases.
Probability Theory and Bayesian Networks.

#### Extra-curricular Activities

**2019-present** Alhub<sup>a</sup> ambassador.

2015-2020 English teaching assistant volunteer at Po Leung Kuk Center for disadvantaged children.2015-2019 Hall Tutor at HKUST UG Hall IV.

#### References

Dr. Yangqiu Song (PhD supervisor). Prof. Dit-Yan Yeung (PhD co-supervisor). (*More references can be provided upon request.*)

ahttps://aihub.org/